Finding Aid for the Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) collection, 1964-1994
UCLA Library Special Collections
Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) collection
1964-1994
1850
UCLA Library Special Collections
4 oversize boxes
The Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) Collection is a mixture of papers and organizational records, publications, ephemera and audio-visual materials collected by organization member Dani Adams (national office in Los Angeles). Of particular interest are the internal memos and complete run of national newsletters produced by the Los Angeles Chapter for national chapter distribution and slides and scripts from the WAVAW slide show, the presentation that chapter members showed to audiences nationwide. There is also extensive coverage of WAVAW's actions against the film "Snuff" and the Rolling Stones's "Black and Blue" advertising campaign and national boycott of Warner Communications, Inc. (WCI).
Women Against Violence Against Women
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dani Adams.
Biography
Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW), a feminist activist organization, was founded in 1976 in Los Angeles by anti-pornography activist Marcia Womongold. The Los Angeles chapter of WAVAW was formed out of an ad hoc coalition of feminist groups who joined forces to protest a film called "Snuff" and the advertising campaign for the Rolling Stones album, "Black and Blue."
WAVAW first began as a reaction to the Los Angeles debut of "Snuff" in March of 1976. This film was advertised as having been made in South America where "life is cheap" and claimed to show the actual murder and dismemberment of a woman. In Southern California this film opened in 22 theatres in Los Angeles and Orange County, including the Mann Theaters. Due to WAVAW protest over the ad and the film, "Snuff" was withdrawn from circulation in the entire Southern California area one week after it opened.
In June of 1976, Atlantic Records-a Warner Communications, Inc. (WCI) subsidiary-put up a billboard on Hollywood's Sunset Strip to advertise the Rolling Stones' album "Black and Blue." It depicted a beaten, bound young woman saying, "I'm 'Black and Blue' from the Rolling Stones and I love it!" WAVAW in cooperation with the California state chapter of the National Coalition for Women (NOW) protested, and the sign was subsequently removed during the night before the group held its press conference beneath the billboard on Sunset Boulevard and picketed at the site.
In response to pressure from WAVAW, Atlantic Records scaled back its "Black and Blue" advertising campaign but did not eliminate it. WAVAW's campaign to stop the use of images of violence against women as an advertising campaign began. When Warner, Elektra and Atlantic Records--subsidiaries of Warner Communications, Inc.--failed to reply to demands that they cease and desist in the use of images of violence against women, and sex-violence, as an advertising gimmick, WAVAW, in coalition with California state chapter of the National Coalition for Women (NOW) called a boycott of all WEA labels (Warner Bros., Reprise, Elektra, Asylum, Nonesuch, Atlantic and Atco) in December 1976. The WCI boycott generated letters from thousands of individuals and organizations such as NOW chapters, YWCA's, and rape crisis hotlines demanding that WCI companies institute a responsible advertising policy. The letter-writing campaign developed as a follow-up to WAVAW's slide show, a presentation of offensive album covers that had been shown to hundreds of women's groups, schools, universities and community organizations across the country.
In 1979, after three years of national protesting, presenting community slide shows, letter-writing, phone-calling, attending shareholders' meetings, leafletting and boycotting, WAVAW secured a policy from Warner Communications, Inc. stating they had agreed to cease and desist with the use of images of violence against women and sex-violence as an advertising gimmick. As a result of the agreement, WAVAW and California NOW ended a three year boycott of WCI Records. On November 8, 1979, WAVAW and WCI made joint statements to the press at dual news conferences in New York and Los Angeles announcing that an agreement had been reached. The agreement announced on November 8, 1979, was presented to the public in the form of a joint press statement, which was negotiated by representatives from WAVAW's national coordinating committee and from the office of David H. Horowitz who is in charge of WCI's record division.
Subsequently, the Los Angeles chapter of WAVAW turned to local projects involving protests against films and campaigns against advertising including the United Artists film Windows in November/December 1980 and Playboy's First Amendment Awards in 1982.
Chronology
1976, Mar "Snuff" campaign
1976, Mar 17-20 "Snuff" opens in 22 theatres in the southern California area and coalitions are formed under the name Women Against Violence Against Women in L.A. and Orange County to stop the showing of the film.
1976, Mar 20 "Snuff" closes in southern California after playing only one week because of coalition efforts
1976, June Atlantic Records (a WCI subsidiary) launched its promotional campaign for the Rolling Stones' album "Black and Blue."
1976, June 20 Atlantic Records has the Rolling Stones billboard on Sunset Strip removed. WAVAW holds press conference in front of where the billboard had been.
1976, Nov WAVAW (in coalition with California NOW) sent letters to each of the WCI record companies demanding that they issue and implement a policy statement against the use of violence against women as an advertising technique.
1976, Dec WAVAW and California NOW called for a boycott of all WCI record labels (Warner/Reprise, Elektra/Asylum/Nonesuch, and Atlantic/Atco).
1977, Jan Articles of Incorporation of WAVAW.
1978, Sept First national WAVAW meeting (in New York City) defined organizational structure (national office in Los Angeles), accountable to local/regional chapters via the national coordinating committee.
1978, May 25 Members of New York WAVAW attended the annual WCI stockholders' meeting.
1979, Nov 8 WAVAW and WCI made joint statements to the press at duel news conferences in Los Angeles and New York announcing that an agreement had been reached.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 66466867
Related Material
This collection forms part of the The June L. Mazer Archive at UCLA.
Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW)
Container List
- Filmex Leafletting., 1976, March.; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Board of Directors., 1976-1983, n.d..; Series 2.; Boxes 1, 2, 3 and 7
  List of Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) Board of Directors; meeting minutes and agendas; internal memos generated by the Los Angeles chapter of WAVAW for distribution to the WAVAW Board of Directors and related correspondence. Includes work files of Julia London, Joan Belknap and Dana Chalberg, who were part of the original WAVAW Board of Directors.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title, and then chronologically by date.
  - Board meetings., 1977-1983.; Boxes 1, 2 and 3
    List of Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) Board of Directors, meeting minutes and agendas, internal memos generated by the Los Angeles chapter of WAVAW for distribution to the WAVAW Board of Directors and related correspondence.
    - Meeting minutes and agenda., 1983, Feb.; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence., 1983, Jan-Feb.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 24)
      List of Board of Directors, internal memos generated by the Los Angeles Chapter of Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) for distribution to the WAVAW Board of Directors and tentative agenda for 1983, Feb Board of Directors Meeting.
      General note
      As of 1982, Apr, Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) Board of Directors included: Susan Curtiss, UCLA adjunct assistant professor and co-founder of the Los Angeles chapter of WAVAW; Patti Giggans, co-founder of Karate Women's School of Martial Arts and self-defense instructor at Santa Monica City College; Joan Howarth, deputy public defender (San Francisco), member WAVAW Coordinating Committee 1977-1980; Julia London, associate director, CALPRIG, Berkeley; co-founder WAVAW and Carol Nelson, director San Fernando Valley Rape Crisis Center, co-chair Southern California Rape Hotline Alliance.
    - Meeting minutes., 1982, Sept, Nov.; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Minutes for meeting to establish Board of Directors., 1977, Jan.; 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Original Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) Board of Directors included: Susan Bechaud, Joan Belknap, Nancy Fried, Dana Chalberg and Julia London, Associate Director, CALPRIG, Berkeley and co-founder WAVAW.
  - Julia London., 1976-1983, n.d..; Box 7
    Meeting minutes, meeting notes, position paper drafts, lecture notes and correspondence generated by or relating to Julia London, Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) Board member and founder.
    - Correspondence., 1976-1983.; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Notes., 1976-1979, [n.d.].; 4 folders (Box 7, Folders 4 - 7)
  - Joan Belknap., 1977-1980, n.d..; Box 7
    Meeting minutes, meeting notes, position paper drafts, lecture notes and correspondence generated by or relating to Joan Belknap, Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) Board member.
    - Notes., 1977-1980, n.d..; 2 folders (Box 7, Folders 8 - 9)
  - Dana Chalberg., 1978-1979.; Box 7
    Meeting minutes, meeting notes, position paper drafts, lecture notes and correspondence generated by or relating to Dana Chalberg, Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) Board member and administrative director of the Women's Center in Los Angeles.
    - Notes and correspondence., 1978-1979.; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Committees., 1977-1983.; Series 3.; Boxes 1, 2, 3, 6, 7, 14 and 15
  Meeting minutes, agendas and related correspondence generated by the Coordinating Committee and National Office Committee of Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) in Los Angeles for national chapter distribution.
  - Coordinating Committee., 1977-1983.; Boxes 1, 2, 3, 6, 7, 14 and 15
    Meeting minutes, agendas and related correspondence generated by the Coordinating Committee of Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) in Los Angeles for national chapter distribution.
    - Meeting minutes and agendas., 1982, Oct-1983, Nov.; 2 folders (Box 1, Folders 20 - 21)
    - Presentation to Board., 1983, Apr.; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 22)
      1983, Apr Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) Coordinating Committee presentation to Board of Advisors entitled "Who WAVAW is Today."
    - Meeting minutes and agendas., 1982-1983.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Meeting minutes and agendas., 1981-1983.; 3 folders (Box 3, Folders 16 - 18)
    - CC L.A. Meeting., 1978, Feb-Mar.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Meeting minutes and agenda, notes, clippings and related correspondence.
  - National Office Committee., 1980.; Box 6
    Meeting minutes and agendas, notes and related correspondence generated by the National Office Committee of Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) in Los Angeles for national chapter distribution.
    - Meeting minutes and agendas., 1980.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Coordinating Committee., 1977-1983.; Boxes 1, 2, 3, 6, 7, 14 and 15
    - Meeting agenda., 1980, May.; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Meeting minutes., 1977, Apr-July.; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 17)
      Includes report from the 1977 Detroit NOW Convention
    - Meeting minutes and agendas., 1982, Apr-Sept.; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 50)
    - Meeting minutes and agendas., 1977, Mar-Nov.; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 22)
- Campaigns., 1974-1986, n.d..; Series 4.; Boxes 6, 9 and 14
  Coverage of the first action of Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW), the "Snuff" campaign, Spring 1976; WAVAW's second action, the "the Black and Blue" campaign, June 1976; WAVAW's major campaign/national boycott of Warner Communications, Inc. (WCI), 1976-1979 and local protests initiated by the Los Angeles chapter of WAVAW.
  - Warner Communications, Inc. (WCI) Boycott., 1974-1982, n.d..; Box 6
    Meeting minutes, notes, position paper drafts, annual reports, articles and clippings, internal memos generated by the Los Angeles chapter for national chapter distribution, letters of protest and form letter responses, protest publicity fliers, press releases and related correspondence relating to WAVAW's major campaign-its national boycott of Warner Communications, Inc. (WCI), the parent company of Atlantic Records, responsible for the "Black and Blue" advertising campaign.
    - 1978 Holiday season campaign., 1978, Oct - Dec.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Correspondence to WAVAW chapters and members and informational packets.
    - Boycott action., 1976, 1977.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Notes and Women's Action Alliance Directory
    - Correspondence., 1976-1979.; 7 folders (Box 6, Folders 6 - 12)
      Letters of support from individuals and groups to WEA/WCI executives and form letter responses received from WEA/WCI executives.
    - Correspondence with Warner Communications, Inc. (WCI) executives., 1976-1979.; 2 folders (Box 6, Folders 13 - 14)
      Mailgram from WAVAW to Ahmet Ertegun, president of Atlantic Records, in connection with WAVAW's effort to persuade Atlantic to cancel the "Black and Blue" advertising campaign; Form letter response from Ahmet Ertegun, chair of the board of Atlantic Records, responding to consumer inquiries about his company's lack of a policy regarding use of images of violence against women; correspondence between WAVAW/California NOW and Joe Smith, the chairman of the board of Elektra/Asylum; correspondence from WAVAW to David Horowitz, head of WCI's record division and correspondence with Bess Myerson, Warner Communications, Inc. (WCI) Board of Directors and Pam Brennan, WAVAW Board member and WCI shareholder, relating to WAVAW's attendance at the 1978 WCI shareholders' meeting in New York.
    - Fact sheets., [1976-1977].; 3 folders (Box 6, Folders 15 - 17)
      WEA Boycott-Letter Writing, List of Album Covers to be Boycotted and WAVAW-Sex Violence and Violence
    - Forms and form letters., 1976-1978, n.d..; 8 folders (Box 6, Folders 18 - 25)
      Drafts and originals of forms, form letters, internal memos generated by the Los Angeles chapter for national chapter distribution, and materials that were included in press and informational packets.
    - Industry correspondence., 1976, Aug.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - MCA Records., 1974-1976.; 2 folder (Box 6, Folders 27 - 28)
      MCA Records annual reports and correspondence to MCA Records executives and related notes.
    - Meeting minutes., 1978, May.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 29)
      Handwritten notes from meeting between Bess Myerson, Warner Communications, Inc. (WCI) Board of Directors and Pam Brennan, Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW) Board member and WCI shareholder, relating to WAVAW's attendance at the 1978 WCI shareholders' meeting in New York.
    - Notes., 1976, Dec, n.d..; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Petitions to CBS., 1977, May.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Policy statement re: violence: other groups., 1979.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Press releases., 1976-1978.; 8 folders (Box 6, Folders 33 - 40)
      1976, July press release mailed to 9000 organizations and individuals nationwide, asking for pressure to be put on the Recording Industry Association of America, No More Black and Blue, issued in response to Atlantic Records' "Black and Blue" advertising campaign; 1978 Holiday Season Campaign press release and WCI boycott press releases including "Joe Smith Meets NOW/WAVAW," "Record Companies Drag Their Feet;"and "Warner Acknowledges Problem but Refuses to Act."
    - Publicity articles., 1976-1977.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 41)
      Copies of Disco DJ, NY Times and Daily Variety articles about or relating to WCI boycott.
    - Publicity flyers., 1976-1977.; 2 folders (Box 6, Folder 42 - 43)
      First WCI/WEA flyer and originals.
    - Record industry correspondence., 1976-1978.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Victory campaign., 1979, Nov.; 3 folders (Box 6, Folders 45 - 47)
      Press releases and joint WAVAW and WCI press statements, victory press packets, publicity articles and notes re campaign victories/histories.
    - Warner Communications, Inc. (WCI) form letter responses., 1977, June-July.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 48)
      Form letter response from Ahmet Ertegun, chair of the board of Atlantic Records, responding to consumer inquiries about his company's lack of a policy regarding use of images of violence against women; related internal memos generated by the Los Angeles chapter for national chapter distribution and related correspondence.
    - WAVAW chapter mailings., 1976, July - 1978, Dec.; 3 folders (Box 6, Folders 49 - 51)
      Internal memos generated by the Los Angeles chapter for national chapter distribution; includes joint WAVAW/CALIF NOW action packets.
    - WAVAW/CALIF NOW., 1976-1977.; 2 folders (Box 6, Folder 52)
      Meeting minutes and related notes.
    - WAVAW/Houston Organization Against Sexism in Media., 1976, Aug.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 53)
      Correspondence, publicity materials, signed petitions and notes.
    - WCI corporate information., 1975-1979.; 2 folders (Box 6, Folders 54 - 55)
      Correspondence to WCI stockholders, 1977 album new releases and clippings and notes related to WCI executives, directors and board members.
    - WCI Strategy., 1977, 1978.; 1 folder (Box 6, Folders 56 - 57)
    - WCI Boycott signed, "Black & Blue Petitions"., 1976 - 1978. (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Films., 1976-1986.; Box 9
    - 9 1/2 Weeks., 1986.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Adult video games., 1982-1983.; Box 9
    - American Multiple Industries (AMI) Adult Video Games., 1982-1983.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Letters of protest against adult video games such as "Custer's Revenge," "Bachelor Party," and "Beat'em and Eat'em" produced by American Multiple Industries (AMI), response letters from AMI, press releases and publicity articles.
  - Films., 1976-1986.; Box 9
    - Beulah Land., 1980, Apr - June.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Bloodline., 1979, June-July.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Snuff., 1976, Mar-May, n.d..; Boxes 9 and 14
    Cease and Desist, chronology of events, notes and correspondence, letters of protest and form letter responses, fact sheets, press releases and protest publicity flyers, clippings and publicity articles and victory campaign press packets relating to the first action of Women Against Violence Against Women (WAVAW), the "Snuff" campaign, Mar/Apr 1976.
    - Cease and Desist., 1976, Mar.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Chronology of Events., 1976, Mar.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Comments and Miscellaneous strategies., 1976, Mar.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Films., 1976-1986.; Box 9
    - Dressed to Kill., 1980, July-Sept.; 2 folders (Box 9, Folders 8 - 9)
  - Snuff., 1976, Mar-May, n.d..; Boxes 9 and 14
    - Endorsements., 1976, Mar-May.; 2 folders (Box 9, Folders 10 - 11)
      Letters of support, press releases and related correspondence from individuals, other organizations and City Attorney/City Council of Los Angeles.
    - Enough Snuff., 1976, Apr - May.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 12)
      Press releases and publicity flyers
  - Media., 1976-1983.; Box 9
    - Eye on L.A.., 1982, Feb-Mar.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Snuff., 1976, Mar-May, n.d..; Boxes 9 and 14
    - Fact sheets for demonstrators., 1976, Mar.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 14)
      When is "Snuff" Opening? Where is "Snuff" being Shown? and Fact Sheet on "Snuff"
  - Films., 1976-1986.; Box 9
    - Film Industry Campaign., 1981-1982.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Media., 1976-1983.; Box 9
    - Firehouse Rape, Tenn., 1979, Oct - 1980, Jan.; 2 folders (Box 9, Folders 16 - 17)
    - Heaven Sent., 1982, May - June.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Hillside Strangler Memorial Event., 1977.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Snuff., 1976, Mar-May, n.d..; Boxes 9 and 14
    - Information for Demonstrators., 1976, Mar.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Films., 1976-1986.; Box 9
    - Lipstick., 1976, Apr - May.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Media., 1976-1983.; Box 9
    - Max Factor FTC Roybal., 1978, Jan.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 22)
      Correspondence between WAVAW, the Federal Trade Commission (FTC) and U.S. Congressman Edward Roybal re the "Self-Defense" advertising campaign undertaken by Max Factor to promote a new line of cosmetics.
  - Snuff., 1976, Mar-May, n.d..; Boxes 9 and 14
    - Nat'l WAVAW demonstrations., 1976, Mar.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Notes and correspondence., 1976, Mar-1977, May.; 3 folders (Box 9, Folders 24 - 26)
      Consists mostly of notes - some correspondence sent/received by WAVAW mostly relating to other women's groups' boycott efforts in southern California.
  - Films., 1976-1986.; Box 9
    - Pieces., 1983, Oct.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Media., 1976-1983.; Box 9
    - Playboy Awards., 1979, June - 1982, Feb.; 4 folders (Box 9, Folders 28 - 31)
      Press coverage of the Playboy sponsored Hugh M. Hefner First Amendment Awards and press releases and statements for the "WAVAW Hugh Hefner Spirit of Playboy Awards," sponsored by WAVAW, Women Against Violence in Pornography and Media (WAVPM), and Women Against Pornography (WAP).
  - Snuff., 1976, Mar-May, n.d..; Boxes 9 and 14
    - Press releases., 1976, Mar-Apr.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 32)
      "Boycott Mann!"; "Feminists Snuff "Snuff"; "Sadism is not Healthy for Women and Other Living Things" and other "Snuff"-related press releases.
    - Publicity., 1976, Apr - May.; 2 folders (Box 9, Folders 33 - 34)
      Publicity articles and newspaper clippings including SNUFF advertisements and theater showtimes.
      Full-sized periodicals rehoused in oversized-boxes 16-17.
    - Signed City of Los Angeles petitions., 1976, Mar 12.; 2 folders (Box 9, Folders 35 - 36)
    - Signed Mann Theater petitions., 1976, Mar 22.; 2 folders (Box 9, Folders 37 - 38)
  - Films., 1976-1986.; Box 9
    - Tattoo., 1981, Sept - Nov.; 5 folders (Box 9, Folders 39 - 43)
  - Media., 1976-1983.; Box 9
    - The Eyes Have It., 1983, July-Oct.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - Snuff., 1976, Mar-May, n.d..; Boxes 9 and 14
    - Theories re Why Snuff., [1976, Mar].; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Victory campaign., 1976, Apr.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 46)
      Press releases and meeting announcement/agenda.
    - Victory publicity packets., 1976, Mar.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Media., 1976-1983.; Box 9
    - WAVAW Media Appearances., 1982.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 48)
      Notes
  - Films., 1976-1986.; Box 9
    - Windows., 1980, June.; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Snuff., 1976, Mar-May, n.d..; Boxes 9 and 14
    - Correspondence to Argentine Embassy., 1976, Mar 12.; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Notes., 1976, Mar-Apr.; 6 folders (Box 14, Folders 6 - 11)
      Revisions to forms, form letters and internal memos including Chronology of Events and other women's group's actions.
    - Notes and correspondence., 1976-1978, [n.d.].; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 12)
      Consists mostly of notes - some correspondence sent/received by WAVAW mostly letters of solicitation from WAVAW to the media and various individuals and groups.
    - Signed City of Los Angeles petitions., 1976, Mar 12.; 2 folders (Box 14, Folders 13 - 14)